Soviet Union and Russia Orthodox Subject Files, Inclusive: 1922 — 2018, undated, Bulk: 1970-1992
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society
Soviet Union and Russia Orthodox Subject Files
Inclusive: 1922 — 2018, undated, Bulk: 1970-1992
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society http://www.baylor.edu/kestoncenter/
16
Keston Institute, 1969 -
56 A4 document boxes.
The Soviet Union and Russia Orthodox Subject Files contain a variety of materials on the affairs of the Russian Orthodox Church, its relations with the state, and the lives of clergy and believers in the Soviet Union and post-Soviet Russia.
Administrative Information
Biography/Profile
Keston College, originally founded in 1969 as the Center for the Study of Religion and Communism with the name changed to Keston College in 1974, collected and publicized details about religious persecution behind the Iron Curtain, becoming “the voice of the voiceless.” After the collapse of communism in the 1990s, Keston College moved to Oxford and downsized due to decreased funding. The name eventually changed to Keston Institute. In 2007, the Institute transferred the Keston Archive and Library to the newly created Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society at Baylor University.
Keston collected, verified, translated, and disseminated information received from believers in the Soviet Union, Poland, Romania, Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Yugoslavia, Bulgaria and other communist and totalitarian countries. The Keston Archive and Library houses numerous letters, petitions, reports and underground publications (Samizdat) from believers of various denominations along with officially published books and periodicals.
From the period from the 1917 Russian Bolshevik Revolution until approximately 2007, Keston obtained materials pertaining to the situation of the Russian Orthodox Church, including living and working conditions of its clergy, persecution of its members, state policies toward the Church, changes to the state law on religion, the state of theological education, and the Church’s involvement in secular affairs.
Historically, the Russian Orthodox Church played a significant role in the life and politics of Russia and the Soviet Union as the largest national religious institution and for 70 years as a major ideological enemy of the state. After the 1917 Russian Revolution, Bolsheviks adopted an aggressive anti-religious policy and enacted religious legislation attempting to eliminate the Russian Orthodox Church. When their attempts to destroy the Church failed, Bolsheviks directly attacked Orthodox clergy and believers. Continuous persecution intensified during the 1921 Famine as the government demanded the individual churches to turn over their valuables to aid the country’s starving population. By the beginning of the World War II, the Russian Orthodox Church was significantly weakened because many clergy died in prisons and labor camps, and without leaders, the number of practicing believers declined.
During the 1941-1945 Great Patriotic War, Josef Stalin relaxed state policy toward the Russian Orthodox Church hoping to boost patriotism and improve Soviet relationships with Ally countries. The Church began to revive. In 1943, the Russian Orthodox Church resumed publication of The Journal of the Moscow Patriarchate.
In the late 1950s, Nikita Khrushchev initiated a new wave of persecution of the Church. His anti-religious campaign became known as the most severe and brutal in history. The government demolished, abandoned, converted to warehouses, or diverted Church buildings for other uses. They arrested, tried, sent to GULAGs, or committed to psychiatric institutions Orthodox clergymen and believers. Aggressive anti-religious propaganda included atheist literature and textbooks, periodicals, public lectures, museum exhibits, documentaries, and posters. The Soviet government controlled all the aspects of cultural life. Strict censorship led to the publication of underground literature or Samizdat. In the late 60s, individuals began to protest the situation of the Russian Orthodox Church and its dioceses.
The 1970s and 1980s marked the rise of Orthodox opposition and an increase of underground religious activity among members of the Orthodox Church. Religious opposition groups included, but were not limited to, Alexander Ogorodnikov’s Christian Seminar, Father Gleb Yakunin’s Committee for the Defense of Believers’ Rights, Maria Group, and “37.” Additionally, KGB agents heavily infiltrated the Orthodox hierarchy and secured internal control of the Church.
Persecution of the Russian Orthodox Church continued until the mid-1980s but declined with Mikhail Gorbachev’s Perestroika. Gradually Church property and rights were restored. In 1988, the Russian Orthodox Church enjoyed the state’s support in celebrating the Millennium of the Baptism or Rus’. Improving church-state relations continued after the collapse of the Soviet Union in 1991.
Scope and Content
The Soviet Union Orthodox Subject Files contain materials about affairs of the Russian Orthodox Church, its relations with the state, and the lives of Russian Orthodox clergy and believers in the Soviet Union. The files consist of newspaper and periodical clippings, bibliographic references, handwritten notes, correspondence, research papers, manuscripts, church and secular publications, radio broadcasting transcripts, and various forms of Samizdat, underground publications and unofficially circulated documents and records.
The materials cover a period from 1922 to 2018 with the bulk from 1970 to 1992. The most notable topics include, but are not limited to, Christian Committee for the Defense of Believers’ Rights, Christian Seminar, 1988 Celebration of the Millennium of the Baptism of Rus’, the 1993 and 1997 changes to Russian religious legislature, and individual accounts of persecution of Orthodox clergy and dissidents. Unofficially circulated documents and records include house search reports, trial transcripts, appeals, addresses, letters from prison, personal testimonies, and literary works.
Some materials pertain to relations between the Russian Orthodox Church and the state in post-Soviet Russia.
Arrangement
Keston received the Soviet Union Orthodox subject files organized by category although some materials were unprocessed. The category system was preserved. The Orthodox subject files were sorted chronologically within categories. The unprocessed Orthodox subject files were organized by categories, whenever possible, or by subject and sorted chronologically.
The Soviet Union Orthodox Subject Files are organized into two series: I. General and II. Samizdat.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 16.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Adel)'geĭm, Pavel, 1938-2013.; Agursky, Mikhail.; Aleksii II, Patriarch Of Moscow And All Russia, 1929 2008.; Aleksiĭ, Patriarch of Moscow and All Russia, 1877-1970.; Barabanov, Evg. (Evgeniĭ), 1943-; Berdi︠a︡ev, Nikolaĭ, 1874-1948.; Bloom, Anthony, 1914-2003.; Borodin, Leonid, 1938-2011.; Dudko, Dmitriĭ.; Ermogen, Archbishop of Kaluga and Borovsk, 1896-1978.; Eshliman, Nikolaĭ.; Filaret, Patriarch of Kiev and all Rus-Ukraine, 1929-; Gorbanevska︠i︡a, Natal)'︠i︡a.; Goricheva, Tatiana.; I︠U︡venaliĭ, Metropolitan of Krutitsk and Kolomna, 1935-; IAkunin, Gleb, 1935-2014.; Ioann, Metropolitan of Saint Petersburg and Ladoga, 1927-1995.; Kapitanchuk, V. A. (Viktor Afanas)'evich); Kirill, Patriarch of Moscow and All Russia, 1946-; Kochetkov, Georgiĭ.; Krakhmal'nikova, Zoia, 1929-2008.; Kukabaka, Mikhas)'.; Lazareva, N. M.; Levitin-Krasnov, A. Ė. (Anatoliĭ Ėmmanuilovich), 1915-1991.; Manuil, Metropolitan of Kuybyshev.; Markus, Sergeĭ; Meerson-Aksenov, Mikhail Georgievich, 1944-; Men)', Aleksandr, 1935-1990.; Nikodim, Metropolitan of Leningrad and Novgorod, 1929-1978.; Ogorodnikov, Alexander, 1950-; Osipov, Vladimir, 1938-; Pimen, Patriarch of Moscow and All Russia, 1910-1990.; Pitirim, Archbishop of Volokolamsk.; Pivovarov, Aleksandr.; Prot︠s︡enko, P. G.; Ratushinskai︠a︡, Irina.; Regelson, Lev.; Senderov, V. A.; Sergiĭ, Patriarch of Moscow and All Russia, 1867-1944.; Shafarevich, I. R. (Igor Rostislavovich), 1923-2017.; Shavrov, Vadim.; Shchipkova, Tat)'i︠a︡na, 1930-2009.; Shiffers, Evgeniĭ, 1934-1997.; Shimanov, G. M. (Gennadiĭ Mikhaĭlovich); Shpiller, Vsevolod, protoireĭ, 1902-1984.; Stepanov, Vladimir.; Svetov, Feliks.; Talantov, Boris Vladimirovich, 1903-1971.; Teodorovich, Nadezhda A., 1907-; Tikhon, Patriarch of Moscow and All Russia, 1865-1925.; Voĭno-I︠A︡senet︠s︡kiĭ, Valentin Feliksovich, 1877-1961.; Volodymyr, Patriarch of Kiev and All Ukraine, 1925-1995.; Voznesenskaia, IUliia.; Zheludkov, S. (Sergiĭ), 1909-
Subjects (Organizations)
Keston College -- Archives.; Keston Institute -- Archives.; Russkaia pravoslavnaia tserkov -- Anniversaries, etc.; Russkaia pravoslavnaia tserkov -- Clergy -- Biography.; Russkaia pravoslavnaia tserkov -- History -- 20th century.; Russkaia pravoslavnaia tserkov -- Soviet Union -- History.; Russkaia pravoslavnaia tserkov zagranitse -- History.; Russkaia pravoslavnaia tserkov. Moskovskaia patriarkhiia.; Vserossiski sotsial-khristianski soiuz osvobozhdeniia naroda.; World Council of Churches.
Places
Soviet Union -- Church history.
Subjects
Children -- Religious life -- Soviet Union.; Christianity and politics -- Russia (Federation); Church and state -- Russkai︠a︡ pravoslavnai︠a︡ t︠s︡erkov)'.; Dissenters, Religious -- Soviet Union -- History.; Freedom of religion -- Soviet Union.; Millennium of Christianity in Kievan Rus, 988-1988.; Nationalism -- Religious aspects -- Russkai︠a︡ pravoslavnai︠a︡ t︠s︡erkov)'.; Patriarchs and patriarchate -- Russia (Federation) -- Biography.; Persecution -- Soviet Union -- History.; Political prisoners -- Soviet Union.; Psychiatric hospitals -- Soviet Union.; Religious education -- Russia (Federation); Religious education.; Underground Literature -- Soviet Union.; Women -- Soviet Union.; Youth -- Religious life -- Soviet Union.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Samizdat.
- General, 1922-2018, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Biography/Profile
  General Orthodox Subject Files contain materials pertaining to the situation of the Russian Orthodox Church and persecution of Orthodox believers under the Communist regime. This series is in good condition.
  - Russian Orthodox Church History. General (1 of 2), 1962-1991 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Russian Orthodox Church History. General (2 of 2), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Russian Orthodox Church History. Living Church, 1966-1977, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Russian Orthodox Church History. Pre-revolutionary Period, 1943, 1953, 1961-1988, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Russian Orthodox Church History. Soviet Period (1 of 8), 1922-1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Russian Orthodox Church History. Soviet Period (2 of 8), 1970-1975 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Russian Orthodox Church History. Soviet Period (3 of 8), 1976-1979 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Russian Orthodox Church History. Soviet Period (4 of 8), 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Russian Orthodox Church History. Soviet Period (5 of 8), 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Russian Orthodox Church History. Soviet Period (6 of 8), 1986-1990 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Russian Orthodox Church History. Soviet Period (7 of 8), 1991 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Russian Orthodox Church History. Soviet Period (8 of 8), 1991-2001, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. General (1 of 2), 1962-1981 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. General (2 of 2), 1982-1991, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Agursky, Mikhail, 1973-1991, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Barabanov, Evgeni, 1973-1979 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Berdyaev, Nicholas, 1968-1975, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Borodin, Leonid, 1983-1987, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Chinov, Anatolii, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Dubrov, Andrei, 1972-1975 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Dzyuba, Yuri, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Ginzburg, Aleksandr, 1977-1987, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Gorbanevskaya, Natal'ia, 1968-1976, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Goricheva, Tat'iana, 1980-1993 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Ivanov, Yuri, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Kapitanchuk, Viktor, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Karelin, Feliks, 1972-1981, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Khodorovich, Sergei, 1976-1986 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Krakhmal'nikova, Zoia, 1982-1995, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Kushev, Yevgeni, 1972-1975 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Lazareva, Natal'ia, 1982, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Levitin (Krasnov), Anatolii (1 of 6), 1968-1973 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Levitin (Krasnov), Anatolii (2 of 6), 1974 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Levitin (Krasnov), Anatolii (3 of 6), 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Levitin (Krasnov), Anatolii (4 of 6), 1977-1981 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Levitin (Krasnov), Anatolii (5 of 6), 1982-1991 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Levitin (Krasnov), Anatolii (6 of 6), undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Levitin (Krasnov), Anatolii. Selected Writings (1 of 4), undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Levitin (Krasnov), Anatolii. Selected Writings (2 of 4), undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Levitin (Krasnov), Anatolii. Selected Writings (3 of 4), undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Levitin (Krasnov), Anatolii. Selected Writings (4 of 4), undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Linitskii, Vitalii, 1981, 1982, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Linitskii, Vitalii. Christmas Cards Account, 1979-1993, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Mandel'shtam, Nadezhda, 1971-1974, 1981, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Maksimov, Vladimir, 1971-1978, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Markus, Sergei, 1984-1992 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Meerson-Aksenov, Fr. Mikhail, 1972-1982 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Ogorodnikov, Aleksandr (1 of 6), 1976-1979 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Ogorodnikov, Aleksandr (2 of 6), 1980-1985 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Ogorodnikov, Aleksandr (3 of 6), 1986 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Ogorodnikov, Aleksandr (4 of 6), 1987 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Ogorodnikov, Aleksandr (5 of 6), 1988-1998, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Ogorodnikov, Aleksandr (6 of 6), undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Ogorodnikov, Aleksandr. Christian Democratic Union of Russia (1 of 2), 1989 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Ogorodnikov, Aleksandr. Christian Democratic Union of Russia (2 of 2), 1991-1998, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Ogorodnikov, Aleksandr. Vestnik Khristianskoi Demokratii, 1990 August-1991 October (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Ogurtsov, Igor (1 of 2), 1977-1978 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Ogurtsov, Igor (2 of 2), 1979-1987, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Osipov, Vladimir, 1975-1995, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Panin, Dmitrii, 1974-1975, 1987, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Pavlovskii, Iurii, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Petrov-Agatov, 1971-1979, 1986, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Ponomarev, Anatolii, 1976-1979, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Poresh, Vladimir, 1979-1987 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Protsenko, Pavel, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Ratushinskaia, Irina (1 of 5), 1981-1986 June (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Ratushinskaia, Irina (2 of 5), 1986 July-October (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Ratushinskaia, Irina (3 of 5), 1986 November-December (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Ratushinskaia, Irina (4 of 5), 1987 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Ratushinskaia, Irina (5 of 5), 1988-2000, 2017, 2018, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Regelson, Lev (1 of 2), 1971-1981, 1988, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Regelson, Lev (2 of 2), 1976, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Rusak, Vladimir, 1980-1989 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Senderov, Valerii, 1983-1987 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Shafarevich, Igor', 1974-1979, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Shavrov, Vadim, 1967, 1973, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Shchipkova, Tat'iana, 1979-1983 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Shiffers, Evgenii, 1970, 1974, undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Shimanov, Gennadii, 1971-1979, undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Shimanov, Gennadii. Writings (1 of 2), 1975 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Shimanov, Gennadii. Writings (2 of 2), 1979 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Shipilov, Vasilii, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Starchik, Petr, 1972-1976 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Svetov, Feliks, 1982-1990, 2002 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Talantov, Boris (1 of 3), 1966-1984, 2006, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Talantov, Boris (2 of 3), 1966 June (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Talantov, Boris (3 of 3), 1967 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Titov, Iurii, 1971-1976, undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Titov, Iurii. Letters, 1970-1972 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Vagin, Evgenii, 1976-1979 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Individual Orthodox Believers. Voznesenskaia, Iuliia, 1976-1981 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Russian Orthodox Church Administration, 1960-1993, undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - List of Russian Orthodox Churches, 1960-1988, undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Individual Russian Orthodox Churches (1 of 2), 1956-1974, undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Individual Russian Orthodox Churches (2 of 2), 1975-1996, 1999, undated (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Russian Orthodox Church. Canon Law, 1976, 1988-1989, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Russian Orthodox Church. Finances, 1961-1979, 1988-1989, 1992 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Russian Orthodox Church. Moscow Patriarchate (1 of 2), 1943, 1960-1999, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Russian Orthodox Church. Moscow Patriarchate (2 of 2), 1970 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Russian Orthodox Church. SOBOR (1 of 2), 1961-1995, 2016 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Russian Orthodox Church. SOBOR (2 of 2), 1971 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Russian Orthodox Church. Dioceses, 1961, 1991, 1998 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Russian Orthodox Church. State. Law, 1959-1977, 1989, 1991, undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Russian Orthodox Church-State Relations. Theory and Practice (1 of 6), 1966-1971 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Russian Orthodox Church-State Relations. Theory and Practice (2 of 6), 1972-1975 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Russian Orthodox Church-State Relations. Theory and Practice (3 of 6), 1976-1979 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Russian Orthodox Church-State Relations. Theory and Practice (4 of 6), 1980-1989 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Russian Orthodox Church-State Relations. Theory and Practice (5 of 6), 1990-1992 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Russian Orthodox Church-State Relations. Theory and Practice (6 of 6), 1993-1998, 2018, undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Russian Orthodox Church-State Relations. Individual Cases, 1975-1981, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Russian Orthodox Church-State Relations. Legislation, 1975-1998 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Russian Orthodox Church-State Relations. Council for Religious Affairs, 1974-1994, undated (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Opening and Reconsecration of Russian Orthodox Churches (1 of 2), 1966, 1975-1990 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Opening and Reconsecration of Russian Orthodox Churches (2 of 2), 1990-1997, undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Registration of Russian Orthodox Churches, 1959, 1975-1991, 1998 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Registration of Russian Orthodox Churches. Naro-Fominsk Case (1 of 2), 1970-1976, 2002, undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Registration of Russian Orthodox Churches. Naro-Fominsk Case (2 of 2), undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Closure of Russian Orthodox Churches, 1969-1970 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Russian Orthodox Church. Commendation in Secular Press, 1969-1989, 1990 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Russian Orthodox Church. Access to Mass Media, 1987-1989, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Oppressive Practices toward the Russian Orthodox Church and Its Members (1 of 3), 1959-1964 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Oppressive Practices toward the Russian Orthodox Church and Its Members (2 of 3), 1965-1973 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Oppressive Practices toward the Russian Orthodox Church and Its Members (3 of 3), 1974-1991, undated (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Harassment of Members of the Russian Orthodox Church, 1976-1989, undated (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Physical Assault Members of the Russian Orthodox Church, 1962-1999, undated (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Russian Orthodox Church. Description of Meetings, 1977-1987, undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Russian Orthodox Church. Fines, 1979-1980 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Interrogations of Members of the Russian Orthodox Church, 1977-1986, undated (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Trials of Members of the Russian Orthodox Church. General, 1962-1987, undated (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Imprisonment of Members of the Russian Orthodox Church. General, 1936, 1963, 1973-1988, undated (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Imprisonment of Members of the Russian Orthodox Church. Borodin, Leonid, 1982-1987 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Imprisonment of Members of the Russian Orthodox Church. Frenkel', Vladimir, 1985-1986 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Imprisonment of Members of the Russian Orthodox Church. Kapitanchuk, Viktor, 1980 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Imprisonment of Members of the Russian Orthodox Church. Khodorovich, Sergei, 1982-1987 (Box 12, Folder 9)